1/tt_H:Hydrogen in a testtube.*Gaseous hydrogen is colourless.
@pmw_H:Hydrogen flame*Hydrogen burns with little or no flame.
@2/tt_He:Helium in a testtube.*Gaseous helium is colourless.
@tt_He2:Glowing white Helium*Helium glows bright white when a high voltage is applied to it.
@pslawinski_He:Helium discharge tube*A helium dischage tube.
@3/tt_Li:Oxidised lithium*This specimen of lithium is coated with a dark layer of oxides and nitrides.
@sc_lepidolite:Violet lepidolite*Lithium is found in trace amounts in the mineral lepidolite.
@4/tt_Be:Beryllium*Small pieces of beryllium.
@es_be_sphere:Beryllium sphere*A 5g bead of 98.5%+ pure beryllium. About 2cm in diameter.
@5/tt_B:Crystalline Boron I*Crystalline boron. 0.2 g.
@es_b:Crystalline Boron II*10 grams of crystalline boron in small pieces.
@6/tt_C:Graphite*One of carbon's many allotropes. 0.2g
@tt_C2:Rough diamonds*Carbon's best known allotrope, diamond. These are rough diamonds from Venezuela. 0.1 g.
@sc_graphite:Piece of graphite*A large piece of graphite, that easily marks paper (as well as your hands!).
@7/tt_N:Gaseous Nitrogen*Gaseous nitrogen is colourless. Amount; 3 ml.
@ot_liN:Liquid Nitrogen*A small amount of liquid nitrogen.
@8/tt_O:Gaseous Oxygen*Gaseous oxygen is colourless. Amount; 3 ml.
@wh_lox:Liquid Oxygen*A small amount of liquid oxygen showing its characteristic light blue colour.
@9/tt_F:Fluor-spar*Elementary fluorine corrodes glass, therefore in place of it is a very old fluor-spar (calcium fluoride) containing traces of radioactive material is shown here. Elementary fluorine is set free by the decay, which is released when breaking the mineral and is recognizable by its characteristic smell. Amount; 0.4 g fluor-spar, fluorine unknown.
@tt_F2:Elementary Fluorine*This is real elementary Fluorine, enclosed in quartz glass, which resists corrosion better than ordinary glass. Amount; 2.5 ml.
@sc_fluorite:Fluorite crystals*Some fluorite fragments, typical of the different pastel shades of fluorite.
@10/tt_Ne:Gaseous Neon*Gaseous neon is colourless. Amount; 3 ml.
@tt_Ne2:Gaseous Neon (glowing)*Applying high voltage to gaseous Neon makes it glow bright orange-red
@pslawinski_Ne:Neon discharge tube*A neon dischage tube.
@11/tt_Na:Shiny Sodium*Beautiful luster without oxidized spots. Amount; 0.2 g.
@swn_Na:Sodium flame*Sodium burns with a beautiful yellow flame.
@12/tt_Mg:Magnesium Ribbon*Small pieces of magnesium ribbon. Amount; 0.1 g.
@es_Mg_ingot:Solid Magnesium*A solid piece of magnesium, 3g, over 2.5cm long. Greater than 99.8% pure.
@sc_dolomite:Dolomite crystals*Some crystals of dolomite from the Tri-State mining district near Joplin, Missouri USA. Dolomite is an commercially important source of magnesium.
@sc_magnesite:Magnesite crystals*These rhombohedral crystals of magnesite measure about 50mm from left to right.
@13/tt_Al:Aluminium foil*0.2 of aluminium foil.
@paf_al:Aluminium foil magnified*A piece of kitchen foil at 60x magnification.
@sc_bauxite:Bauxite*The most important aluminium ore. It was named after the village "Les Baux-de-Provence" in southern France, where it was first discovered in 1821 by geologist Pierre Berthier.
@14/tt_Si:Pieces of silicon*High-purity silicon for the manufacture of silicon chips. Amount; 0.3 g.
@es_si:Pieces of silicon*10 grammes of solid silicon. Greater than 99% pure.
@15/tt_P:White Phosphorus*A small amount of poisonous white phosphorus stored under water to avoid autoignition.
@es_p_red:Red Phosphorus*A pile of (harmless) red phosphorus.
@16/tt_S:Crystalline Sulfur*Crystalline sulfur. Amount; 0.2 g.
@ndgs_S:Sulfur*Sulfur is a component of many of the complex organic compounds that are found in crude oil. It also occurs as hydrogen sulfide in natural gas. This piece of sulfur came from a natural gas plant near Tioga, North Dakota (USA).
@17/tt_Cl:Gaseous Chlorine*Chlorine's green-yellow colour can just be seen here.
@18/tt_Ar:Gaseous Argon*Gaseous argon is colorless. Amount; 3 ml.
@tt_Ar2:Gaseous Argon (glowing)*Applying high voltage to gaseous argon causes it to glow.
@pslawinski_Ar:Argon discharge tube*An argon dischage tube.
@19/tt_K:Potassium*Beautiful luster without oxidized spots. Amount; 0.6 g.
@K_solutions:Potassium compounds*Some potassium compounds, showing their varying colours in water.
@sc_sylvite:Sylvite crystal*A sylvite crystal (potassium chloride in natural mineral form).
@20/tt_Ca:Lumps of Calcium*Some small lumps of calcium. Amount; 0.9 g.
@es_Ca_ingot:Calcium Ingot*A 10 gramme ingot about 2.5cm square. 99% pure.
@sc_gypsum:Piece of Gypsum*A mineral source of calcium, this variety of fibrous gypsum is called satin spar. This specimen is from Verde Valley, Arizona USA.
@21/tt_Sc:Pieces of Scandium*Small pieces of very rare scandium. Amount; 0.1 g.
@es_Sc:Dendritic Scandium*A piece of pure scandium in dendritic form. 10 grammes in weight and 99.5% pure.
@22/tt_Ti:Pieces of Titanium*Small pieces of titanium. Amount; 0.3 g.
@sc_rutile:Rutile*A large piece of rutile, a mineral source of titanium.
@23/tt_V:Lump of Vanadium*A lump of vanadium. Amount; 0.6 g.
@es_Vanadium:Vanadium Cube*A small cube of pure vanadium. Weighs around 10g.
@sc_vanadinite:Vanadinite crystals*Vanadinite is one of the main industrial ores of the metal vanadium and a minor source of lead. This piece is from south west Africa, about 90mm across.
@24/tt_Cr:Crystalline Chromium*Chromium in crystalline form. Amount; 0.2 g.
@es_Cr:Chromium Ingot*A very shiny ingot of chromium. Weighs 10g, 99%+ pure.
@sc_chromite:Chromite*Chromite is the most important mineral source of chrome.
@25/tt_Mn:Pieces of Manganese*Some small pieces of manganese. Amount; 0.8 g.
@sc_psilomeline:Psilomelane*Psilomelane is one of the most abundant manganese ores.
@sc_pyrolusite:Pyrolusite*Pyrolusite is one of the most abundant manganese ores.
@26/tt_Fe:Pure Iron*Pure iron without carbon. Amount; 1.1 g.
@sc_hematite:Hematite*Hematite is an important iron mineral. The specimen is from the Montreal Mine in Hurley, Michigan USA.
@sc_magnetite:Magnetite*Magnetite is an important iron mineral. These octahedral magnetite crystals are from Cerro Huanaquino Potosi, Bolivia.
@27/tt_Co:Lump of cobalt.*A small, 1.0g, lump of cobalt.
@28/tt_Ni:Nickel Sheet*Pieces of nickel sheet. Amount; 0.3 g.
@29/tt_Cu:Copper Wire*A small piece of thick copper wire. Amount; 1.7 g.
@sc_azurite:Azurite*A mineral source of copper. This azurite rose of intergrown crystals comes from Utah, USA.
@30/tt_Zn:Pieces of Zinc*Some small pieces of zinc. Amount; 0.8 g.
@es_Zn:Zinc Ingot*A 50g cast ingot of 99.9% pure zinc. 36mm in diameter and 8mm thick.
@sc_zincite:Zincite crystals*A large piece of zincite, a good source of zinc.
@31/es_Ga:Gallium Rod*A small rod of gallium. Gallium will melt in your hand.
@tt_Ga:Piece of Gallium*Gallium melts just over room temperature. Amount; 0.6 g.
@32/tt_Ge:Pieces of Germanium*Small pieces of germanium. Amount; 0.3 g.
@es_Ge:Germanium piece*A shiny piece of germanium chopped from a larger piece. 10g, 2.5cm long and 99.999% pure.
@33/tt_As:Grey Arsenic*A small piece of grey arsenic. Amount; 0.4 g.
@34/tt_Se:Selenium Shot*Many pieces of selenium shot. Amount; 0.7 g.
@es_Se:Selenium Ingot*Solid selenium ingot weighing around 80g and 7.5cm in diameter. 99.95% pure.
@35/tt_Br:Bromine*Vapours of the pure bromine fill the entire vial. Amount; 0.2 g.
@36/tt_Kr:Gaseous Krypton*Gaseous Krypton is colourless. 3ml.
@tt_Kr2:Gaseous Krypton*Applying high voltage to gaseous krypton causes it to glow light blue. 3ml.
@pslawinski_Kr:Krypton discharge tube*A krypton dischage tube.
@37/zz_Rb:Rubidium Vapour Lamp*A rubidium vapour lamp manufactured by Osram.
@38/es_Sr:Strontium Ingot*A 2.5cm square ingot of 98%+ pure strontium. Approx. 20g.
@tt_Sr:Strontium*A little bit tarnished (oxidised). Amount; 0.2 g.
@sc_strontianite:Strontianite crystal*A group of strontianite (white) crystals, an important strontium mineral.
@39/es_Y:Chunk of Yttrium*A 2.5cm square chunk of yttrium cut from a larger piece. 50g in weight, 99% pure.
@tt_Y:Pieces of Yttrium*Pieces of yttrium. Amount; 0.4 g.
@40/tt_Zr:Pieces of Zirconium*Small pieces of zirconium. Amount; 0.5 g.
@sc_zircon:Zircon crystal*A small zircon crystal. The oldest minerals found so far are zircons from Western Australia, with an age of 4.404 billion years.
@41/es_Nb:Niobium Slug*Solid niobium slug weighing 3.5g. 99.95% pure.
@tt_Nb:Pieces of Niobium*Small pieces of niobium. Amount; 0.7 g.
@sc_pyrochlore:Pyrochlore*Pyrochlore is good mineral source of niobium.
@42/es_Mo:Molybdenum Slug*99.95% pure molybdenum slug weighing 4 g.
@tt_Mo:Molybdenum ribbon*Small molybdenum ribbons. Amount; 0.2 g.
@sc_molybdenite:Molybdenite crystals*Some rounded molybdenite crystals, a good source of molybdenum.
@43/tt_Tc:Pitchblende (containing Technetium)*Technetium is quite radioactive. Pitchblende (an Uranium ore) is shown here, where spontaneous fission of U-238 creates tiny amounts of Technetium. Amount; 0.2 g Pitchblende, corresponding to 0.1 pg or 600 million atoms of Tc.
@44/tt_Ru:Piece of Ruthenium*A chequered piece of ruthenium. Amount; 0.3 g.
@es_Ru:Ruthenium Pellet*A 99.9% pure pellet of solid ruthenium weighing 10g. 14mm in diameter.
@45/es_Rh:Rhodium Pellet*A 1g pellet of 99.9% pure rhodium, 6mm in diameter.
@tt_Rh:Pieces of Rhodium*Rhodium is one of the most expensive precious metals. Amount; 0.4 g.
@46/tt_Pd:Strip of Palladium*Small strip of palladium. Amount; 0.3 g.
@es_Pd:Palladium Ingot*An ingot of pure palladium, 36mm in diameter, 8mm thick.
@47/tt_Ag:Silver Beads*Many beads of silver. Amount; 1.1 g.
@ha_siclm:Silver Ingot*99.1% pure silver ingot. Produced around 1863, from the Chico Ledge Mine, Nevada.
@paf_ag:Silver necklace*A sterling silver chain at 200x magnification.
@48/tt_Cd:Lump of Cadmium*A lump of cadmium. Amount; 0.9 g.
@es_Cd:Cast Cadmium Ingot*A pancake shaped ingot of 99.9%+ pure cadmium. 50g, 36mm in diameter and 8mm thick.
@49/tt_In:Indium*Small piece of indium. 1.3 g.
@es_In:Indium Ingot*Solid indium cast ingot. 28g in weight and 31mm in diameter. 99%+ pure.
@50/tt_Sn:Beads of tin*Beads of tin. Amount; 1.2 g.
@es_snrod:Tin rod*A rod of solid tin weighing 1 kilogram.
@sc_cassiterite:Cassiterite crystals*A group of lustrous cassiterite (tin oxide) crystals.
@51/es_Sb:Antimony Ingot*Cast ingot of 99%+ pure antimony weighing around 40g. 36mm in diameter and 8mm thick.
@tt_Sb:Pieces of Antimony*Small pieces of antimony. Amount; 0.8 g.
@sc_stibnite:Stibnite crystals*A group of stibnite crystals, a source of antimony.
@52/es_Te:Pieces of Tellurium*A beautiful cast piece of pure tellurium showing dazzling crystalline surfaces. 99.9% pure, 30g, 38mm in diameter and 6mm thick.
@tt_Te:Pieces of Tellurium*Small pieces of tellurium. Amount; 0.7 g.
@53/tt_I:Iodine Crystals*Iodine in crystal form at room temperature. 0.7g.
@tt_I2:Iodine Vapour*When heated iodine sublimates (turns from a solid to a gas) into a violet vapour.
@54/tt_Xe:Gaseous Xenon*Gaseous xenon is colourless. 3ml.
@tt_Xe2:Glowing xenon*Applying high voltage to xenon causes it to glow dark purple.
@pslawinski_Xe:Xenon discharge tube*A xenon dischage tube.
@55/tt_Cs:Small Amount of Cesium*Gold-yellow cesium doubly encased in an inner vial. Amount; 50 mg.
@cs_mineral:Pollucite*Pollucite is one of the main cesium minerals.
@56/es_Ba:Barium Ingot*An oxidised barium ingot. 98% pure, 20g, 25mm in diameter.
@tt_Ba:Barium*A little bit tarnished. Amount; 0.5 g.
@57/es_La:Lanthanum Ingot*A solid ingot of 99% pure lanthanum. 75g and 36mm long.
@tt_La:Piece of Lanthanum*The film of lanthanum oxide on the surface makes the metal blue. Amount; 0.4 g
@58/es_Ce:Cerium Ingot*99% pure cerium ingot of about 25g and 20mm in length.
@tt_Ce:Piece of Cerium*The film of cerium oxide on the surface makes the metal blue. Amount; 0.4 g
@59/es_Pr:Praseodymium Ingot*An ingot of 99% praseodymium. Weighs 50g, about 25mm long.
@tt_Pr:Lump of Praseodymium*A lump of Praseodymium. Amount; 0.5 g.
@60/es_Nd:Neodymium Ingot*A 75g ingot of 99% pure neodymium. About 3cm long.
@tt_Nd:A piece of Neodymium*A small piece of Neodymium. Amount; 0.3 g.
@61/tt_Pm:Promethium used on a watch hand*The luminous paint on the hand contains traces of radioactive promethium.
@tt_Pm2:Promethium used on a watch hand (glowing)*Using a long exposure time the glowing can be photographed in the dark.
@62/tt_Sm:Piece of Samarium*A small piece of samarium. Amount; 0.5 g.
@es_Sm:Chunk of Samarium*A piece of samarium that has been chopped off a larger piece. 5g in weight, 99.5% pure.
@63/es_Eu:Europium*This piece of europium shows a multitude of colours due to a thin film of oxidation on the surface. 25g, 99.9% pure, about 2.5cm wide.
@tt_Eu:Piece of Europium*A small piece of Europium. Amount; 0.6 g.
@64/es_Gd:Gadolinium Ingot*A small ingot of 99% pure gadolinium. Weighs 75g.
@tt_Gd:Gadolinium*Gadolinium is the only ferro-magnetic rare earth metal. Amount; 0.4 g.
@65/es_Tb:Terbium Ingot*A 99.5% pure ingot of pure terbium. 25g in weight.
@tt_Tb:Lump of Terbium*A lump of Terbium. Amount; 0.5 g.
@66/es_Dy:Dysprosium Ingot*A 75g ingot of 99% pure dysprosium.
@tt_Dy:Piece of Dysprosium*A piece of Dysprosium. Amount; 0.2 g.
@67/es_Ho:Holmium Ingot*A 75g chunk of holmium. 99% pure.
@tt_Ho:Holmium powder*Holmium powder. Amount; 0.1 g.
@68/es_Er:Erbium Ingot*A 35g ingot of 99.9% pure erbium.
@tt_Er:Swarfs of Erbium*A few swarfs of Erbium. Amount; 0.3 g.
@69/es_Tm:Thulium Chunk*A 25g chunk of 99% pure thulium, one of the rarest of rare-earth metals.
@tt_Tm:Thulium Powder*Thulium powder. Amount; 0.4 g.
@70/es_Yb:Ytterbium Ingot*A 25g of 99.9% pure ytterbium. Notice that the yellow colour is natural.
@tt_Yb:Swarfs of Ytterbium*A few swarfs of Ytterbium. Amount; 0.2 g.
@71/es_Lu:Lutetium Chunk*5g chunk of 99.5% pure lutetium. Considered the rarest of the Lanthanide series.
@tt_Lu:Lutetium Powder*Lutetium powder. Amount; 0.2 g.
@72/tt_Hf:Swarfs of Hafnium*A few swarfs of Hafnium. Amount; 0.5 g.
@73/es_Ta:Pieces of Tantalum*100g of 99.95% pure tantalum in a 38mm square block.
@tt_Ta:Pieces of Tantalum*Pieces of Tantalum. Amount; 1.2 g.
@74/tt_W:Lumps of Tungsten*Small lumps of tungsten. Amount; 0.9 g.
@sc_scheelite:Scheelite crystal*A good source of tungsten.
@75/tt_Re:Sheet of Rhenium*A piece of rhenium sheet. Amount; 0.2 g.
@es_Re:Rhenium Pellet*A one gram pellet, 6mm in diameter. The element with the second highest melting point of all elements. 99%+ pure.
@76/es_Os:Osmium Pellet*A 5g pellet of 99.9% pure osmium, the heaviest metal. 8mm in diameter.
@tt_Os:Osmium Powder*Compressed osmium powder. Amount; 0.4 g.
@77/tt_Ir:Iridium*Small piece of iridium. Amount; 0.9 g.
@es_Iridium:Iridium Rod*Large rod of iridium. Making a rod of this size is very difficult due to iridium's high melting point, extreme hardness and britleness. 22 Troy ounces.
@78/tt_Pt:Strip of Platinum.*A small strip of Platinum. Amount; 0.1 g
@es_ptrod:Solid Platinum Rod*A rod of solid platinum weighing 21 troy ounces. At July 2006 prices this rod is worth around US$25,500.
@79/tt_Au:Gold sheet*A small piece of gold sheet. Amount; 0.5 g.
@ha_gitgm:Gold Ingot*A solid gold ingot from the Tolkuma Gold Mine, New Guinea.
@paf_gold:Gold ring magnified*18ct white and yellow gold ring at 150x magnification.
@sc_gold:Gold crystals*Gold in a vein of quartz.
@80/tt_Hg:Liquid Mercury*A small amount of toxic mercury. Amount; 5.0 g.
@sc_cinnabar:Cinnabar crystals*Some hexagonal cinnabar crystals (red). Cinnabar is the most important mercury mineral.
@81/es_Tl:Thallium Disc*A 10g disk of 99.9% pure thallium. 13mm in diameter and 6mm thick.
@tt_Tl:Thallium Beads*Beads of Thallium. Amount; 1.8 g.
@82/tt_Pb:Piece of Lead*A large piece of lead. Amount; 2.2 g.
@es_Pb:Lead Ingot*A 60g cast ingot of 99.9%+ pure lead, 36mm in diameter and 8mm thick.
@sc_galena:Fluorite crystals*The mineral galena (grey) is the main lead mineral.
@83/tt_Bi:Pieces of Bismuth*Bismuth is the last of the stable elements. Amount; 1.2 g.
@es_Bi:Cast Ingot*A nicely shaped cast ingot of bismuth. 2.5cm wide, approx. 80 grammes. 99%+ pure.
@sc_bismuth:Natural bismuth*A piece of naturally occuring metallic bismuth.
@sc_bismuthsyn:Synthetic bismuth*A bismuth crystal that has been grown in a bismuth smelter. They tarnished to produced the iridescence on the surface.
@84/tt_Po:Pitchblende (containing Polonium)*Po-210 (half life 138 days) is part of the decay chain of U-238, so traces of Polonium exist in the pitchblende shown here. Amount; 0.7 g pitchblende, corresponding to 25 pg or 70 billion atoms of Po-210.
@85/tt_At:Pitchblende (containing Astatine)*At-218 (half life 1.6 seconds) is part of the decay chain of U-238, so traces of Astatine exist in the pitchblende shown here. Amount; 0.2 g pitchblende, corresponding to 0.002 ag or 6 atoms of At-218.
@86/tt_Rn:Trace amounts of Radon.*Rn-220 (half life 56 seconds) is part of the decay chain of Th-232, so traces of Radon are released by the thorium oxide shown here. Amount; 0.9 g Thorium oxide, corresponding to 6 ag or 16000 atoms of Rn-220.
@87/tt_Fr:Pitchblende (containing Francium)*Fr-223 (half life 22 minutes) is part of the decay chain of U-235, so traces of Francium exist in the pitchblende shown here. Amount; 0.1 g pitchblende, corresponding to 0.36 ag or 950 atoms(!) of Fr-223.
@88/tt_Ra:Luminous paint containg Radium salt*This luminous paint contains traces of a radium salt. Amount; 50 mg, Radium fraction unknown.
@tt_Ra2:Luminous paint containg Radium salt (glowing)*With a long exposure time the glowing can be photographed (in the dark).
@89/tt_Ac:Pitchblende (containing Actinium)*Ac-227 (half life 21.8 years) is part of the decay chain of U-235, so traces of Actinium exist in the pitchblende shown here. Amount; 0.1 g pitchblende, corresponding to 12 pg or 30 billion atoms of Ac-227.
@90/tt_Th:Tungsten impregnated with Thorium*A small amount, 0.9g, of tungsten impregnated with thorium, 20mg.
@91/tt_Pa:Pitchblende (containing Protactinium)*Pa-231 (half life 32700 years) is part of the decay chain of U-235, so traces of Protactinium exist in the pitchblende shown here. Amount; 0.2 g pitchblende, corresponding to 37 ng or 100 trillion atoms of Pa-231.
@92/tt_U:Uranium powder*Metallic uranium (U-238) as powder, about 0.1g.
@93/tt_Np:Pitchblende (containing Neptunium)*Np-237 (half life 2.14 million years) is produced by nuclear reactions in U-238, so traces of Neptunium exist in the pitchblende shown here. Amount; 0.4 g pitchblende, corresponding to 47 fg or 120 million atoms of Np-237.
@94/doe_Pu:Plutonium-238 glowing*A small pellet of plutonium glowing under its own light.
@tt_Pu:Small traces in trinitite*This is trinitite, a mineral from the area of the first atomic bomb test in New Mexico. The sand was melted by the heat and encloses traces of Plutonium. Amount; trinitite 0.2 g, Plutonium fraction unknown, but very small.
@95/tt_Am:Small traces in trinitite*This is trinitite, a mineral from the area of the first atomic bomb test in New Mexico. The sand was melted by the heat and encloses traces of Americium, created from Plutonium by neutron capture. Amount; trinitite 0.2 g, Americium fraction unknown, but very small.
@96/tt_Cm:Small traces in trinitite*This is trinitite, a mineral from the area of the first atomic bomb test in New Mexico. The sand was melted by the heat and encloses traces of Curium, created from Plutonium by neutron capture. Amount; trinitite 0.2 g, Curium fraction unknown, but very small.
@#